Finding Aid for James Frederick Lawton papers, 1908-1969
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
James Frederick Lawton papers 1908-1969
Lawton, James Frederick, 1888-1969.
851732 Aa 2; AC; Ac
Berkley, Michigan insurance executive, poet and composer, and active alumnus of the University of Michigan; contain papers relating to activities of the class of 1911, to his involvement in the University of Michigan Club of Detroit, and to his interest in Michigan football, especially the career of coach Fielding H. Yost; also scrapbooks, and manuscripts of poetry and song lyrics.
2.5 linear feet
3 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
2 sound recording tapes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of J. Fred Lawton (donor no. 4107 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
James Frederick Lawton graduated from the University of Michigan with an A.B. degree in 1911. While at the University, Lawton played end on football team coached by Fielding H. Yost. Lawton had a deep affection for Yost and for the University, and though his career was spent as an insurance executive, he maintained ties with the U-M through his poetry and musical compositions and through his activities as a loyal alumnus. In 1911, later in the year of his graduation, Lawton with Earl V. Moore composed the words and music to "Varsity" a song that became traditional to the U-M Marching Band.
The papers of J. Fred Lawton contain material relating to activities of the class of 1911, to his involvement in the University of Michigan Club of Detroit, and to his interest in Michigan football, especially the career of coach Fielding H. Yost; also scrapbooks, and manuscripts of poetry and song lyrics. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Poetry, musical compositions, and other writings; University of Michigan Class of 1911; University of Michigan Club of Detroit; Topical files; Photographs; Scrapbooks; and Sound Recordings.
Subjects:
Berkley (Mich.); Lawton, James Frederick, 1888-1969.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan Club of Detroit.; University of Michigan. Class of 1911.; University of Michigan--Football.; University of Michigan--Songs and music.; Yost, Fielding Harris, 1871-1946.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Buildings--Michigan--Detroit.; Central High School (Detroit, Mich.); Detroit (Mich.)--Buildings.; Detroit (Mich.)--Streets.; Lawton, James Frederick, 1888-1969.; Lawton family.; Michigan daily.; Michigan Union Opera.; Michigamua.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Streets--Michigan--Detroit.; Sphinx (Fraternity: University of Michigan); Trigon (Fraternity: University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae.; University of Michigan. Class of 1911.; University of Michigan--Football.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; University of Michigan--Track and field.; World War, 1914-1918.; War bonds and funds.; Yost, Fielding Harris, 1871-1946.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Lawton, James Frederick, 1888-1969.; University of Michigan--Songs and music.; University of Michigan--History.; Yost, Fielding Harris, 1871-1946.
Contributors:
Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Couzens, James, 1872-1936.; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.; Dondero, George Anthony, 1883-1968.; Elbel, Louis.; Guest, Edgar A. (Edgar Albert), 1881-1959.; Hatcher, Harlan, 1898-1998.; Hill, Norman Hingston, 1887-1971.; Humphrey, George M. (George Magoffin), b. 1890.; Johnson, Hugh S. (Hugh Samuel), 1882-1942.; Mack, Connie, 1862-1956.; Mattern, David Earl, 1890-1959.; Moore, Earl Vincent, 1890-1987.; Murfin, James Orin, 1875-1940.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Norton, William J. (William John), 1883-1975.; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Yost, Fielding Harris, 1871-1946.; Zeder, Fred, 1886-
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Posters.; Sound recordings.
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1909-1919 (Box 1)
  - 1921-1929 (Box 1)
  - 1930-1933 (Box 1)
  - 1934-1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940-1943 (Box 1)
  - 1944-1948 (Box 1)
  - 1949-1952 (Box 1)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957 (Box 1)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960 (Box 1)
  - 1961 (Box 1)
  - 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - 1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - 1969 (Box 1)
- Poetry, musical compositions, and other writings
  - Poems and song lyrics, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Music
    - 1908-1909 (Box 1)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts and articles
    - Description of Fielding H. Yost's career at Michigan, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Description of experience as a Detroit juvenile court probation officer 1911-1914 (Box 1)
    - "Methods of Securing Prospects"(insurance article) 1919 (Box 1)
- University of Michigan Class of 1911
  - Minutes 1907-1911 (Box 1)
  - Thirty year reunion (Box 1)
  - Fifty year reunion
    - Correspondence
      - A-B (Box 1)
      - C (Box 1)
      - D-E (Box 1)
      - F-G (Box 1)
      - H (Box 1)
      - I-K (Box 2)
      - L-M (Box 2)
      - N-Q (Box 2)
      - R (Box 2)
      - S (Box 2)
      - T-V (Box 2)
      - W-Z (Box 2)
    - Golden anniversary fund (Box 2)
    - Emeritus dinner Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- University of Michigan Club of Detroit
  - Historical material
    - 1916-1928 (Box 2)
    - 1928-1929 (Box 2)
    - 1929-1932 (Box 2)
    - 1932-1935 (Box 2)
    - 1935-1945 (Box 2)
    - 1947-1953 (Box 2)
  - Lecture course 1930-1937 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - History Committee correspondence, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Bulletins
    - 1954-1957 (Box 2)
    - 1958-1960 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
- Topical files
  - Biographical (Box 2)
  - Camp Happy Hollow (Box 2)
  - Central High School (Box 2)
  - Citations and awards (Box 2)
  - Liberty Loan Committee of Detroit and Wayne County, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Michigamua (Box 2)
  - Michigan Union Opera posters (autographed) (Folder 1)
  - University of Michigan Football (Box 2)
  - Yost, Fielding H., 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Photographs
  - Portraits; with wife; with dignitaries (Box 2)
    (see also outsize folder, Ac)
  - Early photos (Box 2)
  - Detroit Central High School (Box 2)
    (see oversize folder)
  - U-M student activities
    - Class games, Union Opera, Michigan Daily (Box 2)
    - Classmates (Box 2)
    - Football and track (Box 2)
    - Men's Glee Club (Box 2)
    - Michigamua, Sphinx, Trigon (Box 2)
      (see also oversize folder)
  - U-M alumni activities
    - Class of 1911 reunions (Box 2)
    - Football 1930s-1940s (Box 2)
    - Songs display and miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Awards, presentations, meetings (Box 2)
  - Photos and portraits of others (Box 2)
  - World War I Liberty Loan rally (Box 2)
  - Detroit view 1880s(old Capitol Union School) (Box 2)
  - Yost, Fielding H. (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks (including clippings, letters and ephemera)
  - 1922-1925 (Volume 1)
  - 1926-1933 (Volume 2)
  - 1955 (trip to Europe) (Volume 3)
  - 1942 re All Army-Detroit Lion football game (Box 3)
  - 1944-1948 (Box 3)
  - Loose clippings, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Sound recordings
  - Discussion with Lawton and others about Fielding H. Yost, the writing of the Victors, and other university-related topics, 2 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes; 7 in.; 3 3/4 ips (Box 1)